we're going to have another catastrophe
sooner than later it'll be bigger than
2008 but the next one is going to be
strike three we've had two warnings
they've been ignored the third time it's
game over we are entering a period of
financial crisis that is the greatest
the world has ever known the wealth
transfer that will take place during
this decade is the greatest wealth
transfer in history wealth is never
destroyed it is merely transferred and
that means that on the opposite side of
every crisis there is an opportunity the
great news is that all you have to do to
turn this crisis into your great
opportunity is to educate yourself I
believe that the best investment that
you can make in your lifetime is your
own education education on the history
of money education on finance education
on how the global economy works
education on how all of these guys the
central bankers with stock market how
they can cheat you how they can scan you
if you learn what is going on and how
the financial world works you can put
yourself on the correct side of this
wealth transfer with Patricia once said
that the further you look into the path
the further you can see into the future
this program it's all about creating
your own crystal ball being able to gaze
into the future being able to change
this crisis the greatest crisis in the
history of mankind into your great
opportunity
[Music]
hi in the last episode of hidden secrets
of money I spoke with Harry dent about
deflation and the reason that we both
feel that it's absolutely inevitable in
the bonus feature
I talked with Harry about some of our
differences and he believes that it's
going to be a long drawn-out deflation I
believe it's going to be a very
short-lived deflation followed by
potentially a hyperinflation and the
reason is something we're going to talk
about in this episode and it's velocity
of currency and that is all controlled
by psychology I'm very fond of saying
that the economy is both psychological
and psychological it runs in waves and
cycles and those waves and cycles are
very logical because of this psychology
that's going on behind it and that
psychology controls the velocity of
currency now I like to teach through the
looking-glass of history so I'm going to
read you a little bit of my book because
there's a perfect example of this in the
Weimar hyperinflation and after I'm done
with the book we're going to come back
and we're going to look at some data so
you get a full understanding of what
velocity of currency is and how it
affects you so on page 16 we have at the
beginning of World War one Germany went
off the gold standard and suspended the
right of its citizens to redeem their
currency the mark for gold and silver
like all wars World War one was a war of
and by the printing press the number of
marks in circulation in Germany
quadrupled during the war prices however
had not kept up with the inflation of
the currency supply so the effects of
this inflation were not felt the reason
for this peculiar phenomenon was because
in times of uncertainty people tend to
save every penny and World War one was
definitely
time of uncertainty so even though the
German government was pumping tons of
currency into the system no one was
spending it yet the by war's end
confidence flooded back along with the
currency that had been on the sidelines
and the ravaging effects worked their
way through the country as prices rose
to catch up with the previous monetary
inflation just before the end of the war
the exchange rate between gold and the
mark was about 100 marks per ounce but
by 1920 it was fluctuating between 1,000
and 2,000 marks per ounce
retail prices shortly followed suit
rising by 10 to 20 times anyone who
still had the savings they had
accumulated during the war was
bewildered when they found it could only
buy 10 percent or less of what it could
just a year or two earlier then all
through the rest of 1920 and the first
half of 1921 inflation slowed and on the
surface the future was beginning to look
a little brighter the economy was
recovering business and industrial
production was up but now there were war
reparations to pay so the government
never stopped printing currency in the
summer of 1921 prices started rising
again and by July of 1922 prices had
risen another 700 percent this was the
breaking point and what broke was
people's confidence in their economy and
their currency having watched the
purchasing power of their savings fall
by 90% in 1919 they knew better this
time around they were smarter they had
been here before all at once the entire
country's attitude toward currency
changed people knew that if they held on
to their currency for any period of time
they get burned the rising prices would
wipe out their purchasing power
suddenly everybody started to spend
their currency as soon as they got it
the currency had become a hot potato and
no one wanted to hang on to it for a
second now on the next page I talked
about the front page of the New York
Times 1923 and I referenced some
information there and I just happen to
have a reprint of the front page of the
New York Times from 1923 and there's an
article here about the German
hyperinflation but what I find more
interesting than that is the entire
paper is this wonderful time capsule and
if you replaced the names and dates in
and names of countries and so on and
most of these articles it would all be
pertinent today you'd think that you
were reading today's newspaper but when
it comes to this article on the German
hyperinflation it talks about these
paper mills pumping out 45 billion marks
per day now this is the February edition
of the New York Times by November those
paper mills were pumping out five
hundred quadrillion marks per day so now
we're going to take a look at velocity
and how it could affect us in the future
so this is me now I developed this
keynote presentation to make
understanding velocity easy most
economists make it sound really complex
and people don't think they can
understand it but stick with me I think
you'll enjoy this when you're measuring
velocity you're measuring the number of
times each unit of currency changes
hands I'm going to have lunch and I'm
going to pay the waiter I'm going to tip
him a buck and then he parked in the red
zone that smart morning so his car got
towed he's going to have to take a cab
home and he's going to pay that cab
driver that same dollar when he gets to
his destination then later on that day
the cab driver is going to have to fill
his cab with gas and he's going to use
that same dollar again as part of the
payment
for his tank of gas so that dollar was
used in one-two-three transactions it
had a velocity of three that day in
other words one dollar about three
dollars worth of goods and services now
we're going to kick this up a notch and
we're going to call this a country of
ten people this economy of just ten
people and their currency supply is one
dollar that's the only dollar that
exists and it circulates once and so
you've got one dollar times the velocity
of one equals a GDP the health of the
size of the economy is one dollar if it
circulates twice it's two three four
five six seven eight nine ten so one
dollar times the velocity of ten or ten
transactions equals a ten dollar GDP the
health of that economy now if you expand
the currency supply we've given each one
of these people one dollar if they all
make a transaction there has now been
ten transactions but each dollar was
only involved in one of them so it's a
currency supply of ten dollars times one
transaction each equals a ten dollar GDP
so even though you've got ten times the
currency supply the economy has the same
vibrance there was ten transactions it
equals ten dollars then we have a second
transaction a third a fourth this could
be a healthy economy it could also be a
tenth economy running into
hyperinflation keynesian x' that's the
type of economists that are running the
modern-day economy believe that you can
create a healthy economy by changing
this figure here the size of the
currency supply so the Federal Reserve
thinks that by adding currency to the
economy that they're going to be able to
stimulate it and make the economy grow
and the thing is it isn't the quantity
of currency it's the amount of goods and
services that are created in that
country that determines the country's
level of prosperity so if you just add a
bunch of currency all it's going to do
eventually is drive up prices velocity
will slow at first and that's what we're
seeing now well the same thing happened
in Weimar Germany this is the entire
hyperinflation from the beginning of
World War one in 1914 until the end of
1923 and most economists are attracted
to this big hyperinflation on the end
but one thing I discovered when I was
writing my book is that there's almost
always a pre hyperinflation
hyperinflation and we see one here where
there's this rise of prices and quantity
of currency and then it levels off for a
little while and then rises again and
this has to do with the psychology this
is the time where I said those people
had been there before and experienced
that I'm going to zoom up on it and so
here you see the currency supply
increasing so they're they're doing
monetary inflation but prices stay level
in the price of gold actually dropped
toward the end of the war but as soon as
the anxiety is lifted from the
population and they start feeling better
all of that currency comes out of hiding
and people start making transactions and
velocity picks up and prices and the
price of gold especially just rose
dramatically and then leveled off some
16 times higher than they were
originally notice that the currency
supply is growing at a certain rate the
prices are delayed and then BAM they
rise to meet it and exceed it and then
stabilize where to account for that
quantity of currency the back to this
original chart here what I find
interesting is that during the war it
lagged and then it caught up and matched
the currency supply but then as they
kept on printing velocity started to
exceed the currency supply so prices
started to rise
faster than they were printing currency
and and that's the endgame for a
hyperinflation the big lesson here is
that the people who owned gold and
silver instead of the national currency
came out relatively unscathed or even
made huge gains in their purchasing
power now this is the u.s. currency
supply from 1918 until today and we've
created all of this currency but we
haven't seen any ravaging inflation yet
and that is because velocity has fallen
to compensate for the creation of
currency but there will come a time when
the psychology of the of the country
changes and you will see after this
short term deflation where velocity
falls even further you will then see the
velocity pick up and prices will rise
and we I believe that we will go into a
hyperinflation because they're going to
create more currency than this and that
currency is going to be sitting there
and velocity will have slowed and slowed
and slowed to compensate it until
something changes psychologically the
beginning of every hyperinflation looks
like everything is okay again the
economy gets better velocity picks up
and and and that's the really danger
point and nobody can see it as velocity
starts picking up right of course
there's a name for that it's called
money illusion which is before the
inflation really kicks in and and other
gets extremely turns into hyperinflation
there is this feel-good period where you
know there's more money around and you
know unemployment dropping and people
feel more prosperous the price is having
quite skyrocket yet it's all losery
because it will go away once the price
level adjust but there is that kind of
you know period in between and it is a
feel-good period but it doesn't last
very long
but you're making a very good point
which is a lot of people assume that
inflation is a function of money supply
or money printing and that's not right
it's a partial function of money supply
but the other part of the function is
behavioral it has to do a velocity which
is just a psychological phenomena you
know do you feel good you want to go out
for dinner do you want to take
friends you want to take a vacation or
do you want us down leave your money in
the bank and watch TV those are two
different states of the world based a
lot on your confidence and how do you
feel both things have to come together
to get the kind of inflation the Fed
ones now here's the problem they can
make the money supply whatever they want
they're certainly printing trillions of
dollars we understand that so far they
have not been able to bend the velocity
curve they have not been able to get you
and me and everyone else in America and
around the world to spend more money but
let's say they do they change the
psychology they change the behavior once
you change it it's very hard to change
your back it's not it's not like filling
an on/off switch I mean it's taken years
for the Fed to you know kind of try to
inject inflation scared try to get some
inflation but what if it actually comes
what if inflation goes from 1% to 3% and
matters six months and stays there looks
like it's going to three and a half
percent well the next stop is 10% it's
not the Fed thinks they can dial it back
down to two and a half which we're that
which is what they say they want but
what they'll find is once that once that
velocity once that behavioral genie is
out of the bottle they won't be able to
get it back in it will take off it'll
take on a life of its own what's the PHA
going to do you know raise interest
rates of 10 percent with unemployment at
7 percent I mean though people go down
and burn down the feta mean their their
limits on what they can do it but the
point is once it starts and you're
exactly right it's a feedback loop it
feeds on itself the Fed thinks they can
control it they're wrong the behavioral
aspect of it will be out of control and
I guess a we'll be on our way to 10% if
not worse
it seems like all of these bright minds
that want to run things
none of them trust the free market
mechanism well I think that's right they
they will talk to you our nauseum about
the failures of the free markets without
realizing that most of the so-called
failures are actually the result of
misguided government policies from prior
times I'll give you a classic example
1998 was a warning that's you know
started in 1997 capital outflows from
emerging markets started in Thailand it
was blood in the streets and in Jakarta
and Seoul made its way to Russia Russia
imploded took down the hedge fund
long-term capital management I was
associated with that so I had a
front-row seat on that disaster and
finally the world built a firewall
around Brazil and Brazil did not
collapse Allah would have been the next
Domino to fall now there was a clear-cut
lesson capital markets came within hours
of complete closure night I was there I
said with Peter Fisher who was head of
open market operations of the Fed his
associate dean across three on the phone
bill McDonough president of the Federal
Reserve Bank of New York Gary Gensler
was there from the Treasury all the
lawyers all the bankers on Wall Street
we were trying to hold this together now
we did bring it in for a soft landing so
the world has kind of forgotten about
that episode but it was extremely close
and extremely delicate we were literally
hours away from shutting down global
bond markets and and stock market now
what lessons rely well the lesson that
cascades into the credit card not
working in the gas coming out not coming
up around that that's right there would
have been a global bank holiday we and
we were hours away from that now it
didn't happen sir everyone's like oh no
big deal that's fine you know but there
were some lessons that should have been
learned you know banks should have been
broken into smaller units derivatives
should have been banned you know etc
there were things that should have been
learned from that instead what did we do
we did the opposite we repealed
glass-steagall which allowed banks to be
hedge funds we repealed swaps regulation
which allowed them to create swaps and
derivatives on all kinds of other things
that had never been done before we
repealed in that capital rule for broker
dealers so instead of 15 to 1 leverage
you rely about 30 to my leverage which
Lehman had on the day I went down we we
implemented Basel 2 which allowed banks
to use more leverage we did the exact
opposite of what we should have learned
in
is it any surprise but ten years later
we have a bigger catastrophe almost
destroyed capital markets again and now
here we are not learning the lessons
again
we haven't done anything we need to do
so therefore we're going to have another
catastrophe sooner than later it will be
bigger than 2008 but the next one is
going to be strike three we've had two
warnings that have been ignored the
third time it's game over I don't see
any particular difference between my
outlook at yours certainly a situation
where society owes more than can pay and
where it has to default either on asleep
or dishonestly is deflationary deadly
actually being on default we are
bankrupt we can't pay ya dishonestly
inflating the debt away exactly exactly
honestly would be to say to the
bondholders yet that's right we say
we're going to pay it back and we serve
and pay it back with interest
well too bad so sad times are tough we
lied strongly or followed right say the
guys like me you're 60 yep I know you're
supposed to get Social Security when
you're 62 or 65 the truth is we don't
have the money so you're not going to
get it right that's the honest right I
think the yield politician is very low
which regards to the honest way so I
think that we're going to have
deflationary scares and I think we're
going to have deflationary events I
think we're going to have asynchronous
events like long-term capital management
and things like that that will initially
have deflationary outcomes but I suspect
like you that the demand for the public
will be for the big thinkers to solve
that problem and solve it in the only
way they know how which is to fill every
crack even the Grand Canyon with
currency so how is this all going to
play out you know I don't know exactly
but what I do know is that the longer
this goes on the bigger it's going to be
and I wrote about the past some of the
possibilities in my book and this was
written before the crisis of 2008 and so
in here i refer to ben bernanke but i'm
going to change that to just the Federal
Reserve or central banks
for you right now so the day of
reckoning will come when millions of
baby boomers reach the age where they
have to take mandatory distributions
from their IRAs as they find that the
investments they were counting on for
their retirement their homes and their
IRAs full of mutual funds have actually
lost value that the amount of stuff that
they can buy from the proceeds if they
sell their home is actually less than
when they bought their home and as they
realized that their dream of a
comfortable retirement was just that a
dream all those boomers will get scared
and pull in their horns they will stop
spending they will start selling off
their assets and the greatest stock
market crash in history will unfold as
more and more boomers panic and sell I
believe this will also be accompanied by
the greatest real estate crash the world
has ever known this perfect storm of
bankruptcies and foreclosures will cause
the currency supply to contract as the
giant credit bubble pops and all those
big spenders become big savers when
people save their currency it stops
circulating the economic engine runs out
of oil and the whole thing locks up this
is every central bankers worst nightmare
this is real deflation and the world's
central bankers are about to discover
the true scale of the horrors of a
credit bubble implosion when this
happens the Federal Reserve will once
again send out its Armada of money bomb
dropping helicopters but this time
something will be different something
will have gone horribly wrong the bombs
will have been defused the Fed will try
pumping the banking sector by buying up
every kind of debt they can get their
hands on but to no avail they will go to
the extraordinary measures that they had
said they were prepared to go to they
will buy every mortgage mortgage-backed
security and any other type of debt
that panicky investors and banks are
trying to sell but nothing good will
come of it they will start buying stocks
to buoy the stock market but retail
sales will continue to plunge they will
try broad-based tax cuts but it won't
jumpstart the economy they will work
with foreign central banks to buy each
other's debt but the global economy will
continue to plummet people will finally
see through the veil they will see what
Dorothy the Scarecrow the lion and the
Tin Man saw that The Wizard of Oz is
really just some dopey old guy
frantically pulling levers remember when
we talked about how during World War one
the Germans increased their currency
supply by 400% yet there was no price
inflation because of the public's
anxiety over the war and the uncertainty
of their future imagine the anxiety 75
million baby boomers will feel as they
approach retirement only to find their
homes and their mutual funds are now
worth next to nothing the nest egg
ladies and gentlemen has just cracked
when they get their tax rebates are they
going to buy that new big-screen TV and
the latest cell phone I think not I
think they're going to save every dime
they can get their hands on
just like in Germany during the war but
there will be a point at which a
threshold is reached for each income
class it will be different it will be
the point where they feel that they
finally got enough save for retirement
for some it will be $100,000 for others
it will be $1,000,000 and for others
still it will be 10 million dollars the
Fed knows there is a point where they'll
finally feel safe enough to replace that
aging computer and maybe get that new TV
at this point the boys of the Fed will
buy enough government debt to fund tax
rebates for all the taxes in the
previous year but still nobody will buy
that
the threshold the Fed is looking for
will not be reached then in not so quiet
desperation the Fed will say screw the
helicopters send in the Bombers and as
the shadow of millions of stealth
currency bombers darken the skies
currency will begin to fall like rain in
the desert as Joe Sixpack and John Q get
tax rebate checks in the mail for all
the taxes they paid during their entire
lifetimes fear will be temporarily
alleviated and some of that currency
will come out of hiding
just as in Weimar Germany prices will
rise quickly and dramatically as all
that stored up currency energy is
released in a panic the Fed will call
back the Bombers but it will be too late
there's nothing they will be able to do
to stop it now because the
hyperinflation will have already begun
the Dow will begin an invisible crash of
epic proportions and gold prices will
shoot to the moon if you are wise enough
to moor your boat in the safe harbors of
gold and silver and other commodities
you will weather the storm it won't be
pretty but at least you'll be safe at
this point confidence in the currency
will fall faster than it can be created
cost of living increases for government
employees and the costs of all
government projects the subcontractors
the labor the materials will all
skyrocket and each time more currency is
created to pay for the increases the
value of the currency will fall even
faster in times like that governments
have only two choices shut down the
government on all of its projects and
services send everybody home without pay
turn off the printing presses and wait
for the free market system to discover
price levels that account for the
quantity of the currency in the supply
or print the currency into oblivion
governments have always chosen the
latter but the stored up energy of
excess currency creation doesn't have to
take place within the United States and
it doesn't necessarily have to be in the
future in fact there is an abundance of
stored up currency just waiting to be
released right now as I mentioned
earlier all the dollars we sent overseas
to other countries to buy their goods
and services are now sitting in their
bank accounts just waiting to be spent
eventually the world economy will lose
faith in the US dollar and will want to
dump it by buying up goods and as all
those dollars come flooding back into
the US it will of course cause the
prices of those goods and services to
rise and could and probably will trigger
a scenario much like the one I have just
finished describing throughout history
economists have suffered from what I
like to call this time Syndrome
this time they've become masters of the
economic universe this time they've
figured it out this time they've tamed
the economy this time they've mastered
the art of infinite currency
amplification this time a fiat currency
will work history gives this a
probability of zero each time we sailed
toward economic doom the greatest
financial minds in the world were at the
helm do you really think we should
continue letting them steer the ship I
think not it would be nice if we started
listening to people that have been right
rather than the people that have
theories and it would be great if they
would allow the free market to work but
that's not the way it's going to happen
the people that have the theories will
continue to rule and we will vote for
people that don't know what they're
doing and so the best that we can do is
try to protect ourselves and even you
know potentially benefit from
government and economists stupidity and
so the way to do that is by learning as
much as you can about what's happening
and developing your own opinions on what
is coming at you rather than being
reactionary and you can do that by
watching some of the bonus features just
click the info button and we'll see you
in the bonus feature and until next time
until the next episode see you there one
of the most important things is how to
prepare for all of this so that you can
be able to see through that economic
veil and understand what's going on when
things start to shift